Gleb Derujinsky Papers
Gleb Derujinsky Papers
1919-1964
Derujinsky, Gleb W., 1888-
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American sculptor, born in Smolensk, Russia; died in 1975. Correspondence, with, among others, Archer M. Huntington and Ronald Lane Latimer, 1925-1960; photoprints; published material about Derujinsky, 1922-1964; and an original sketch.
148939
Biographical History
Gleb Derujinsky (1888-1975) was born in Smolensk, Russia, to aristocratic parents (his father held a position comparable to that of a United States Senator), and emigrated to the United States in 1919. Derujinsky studied at the University and Fine Art Academy at Petrograd and was a member of the National Sculpture Society, the National Academy of Design, and the American Artists Professional League. He received awards from his home country as well as from the Paris World's Fair (1937), the National Academy of Design (1938), the National Arts Club (1961), and the American Artists Professional League, and twice received the Henry Hering Memorial Medal awarded by the National Sculpture Society.
His work has been exhibited at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and at the Royal Academy in London and in Belgium. His sculptures may be seen at major museums as well as many churches and public buildings, both in the United States (Metropolitan Museum of Art, the New School for Social Research, and Brookgreen Gardens) and abroad (Panama Canal Zone, Jesuit mission on Mocameh, India).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gleb Derujinsky Papers consist of biographical material (a published biographical sketch of Derujinsky), correspondence (both incoming and outgoing), a few subject files (contract, sketch, award, a few photographs), and published material (church bulletins, exhibit notices, newspaper clippings, pemphlets, programs).
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically, outgoing is arranged chronologically. All other material is arranged alphabetically within its series.
Related Material
has the papers of many notable sculptors and artists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Derujinsky, Gleb W., 1888- -- Archives.; Huntington, Archer Milton, 1870-; Latimer, Ronald Lane.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Russian Americans.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Programs (documents); Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical sketch of Derujinsky (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - A, 1925; 1940-1941,; 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Baumann, Brother C., 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Beaux Arts Institute of Design, 1925-1926; 1928 (Box 1)
    - B, 1925-1928; 1940,; 1942,; 1947,; undated (Box 1)
    - C, 1942 (Box 1)
    - D, 1937; 1939,; 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - Eggars and Higgins, 1950 (Box 1)
    - F, 1927; 1941-1942,; 1948,; 1960 (Box 1)
    - First National Congress of Catholic Artists, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Fordham University, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - G, 1942; 1947 (Box 1)
    - H, 1929; 1944,; 1947,; 1949,; 1956 (Box 1)
    - Hunting, Archer Milton, 1948-1954 (Box 1)
    - I, 1943; 1947 (Box 1)
    - Jennings-Jhodanski, 1930; 1937-1938,; 1940 (Box 1)
    - Kent School, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - K-L, 1937; 1941,; 1944,; 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - Latimer, Ronald Lane, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - M, 1939; 1949,; 1957,; undated (Box 1)
    - N-New York World's Fair, 1928; 1933,; 1938,; 1940,; 1943-1944,; 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - P, 1927-1928; 1936-1937,; 1940-1942 (Box 1)
    - Rachmaninoff', Sergei, 1942 (Box 1)
    - R, 1929; 1946-1947,; 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - S, 1937; 1941-1942,; 1945,; 1948,; 1950,; 1953,; 1956-1957,; 1959 (Box 1)
    - Toggard-Treasury Department, 1938; 1950 (Box 1)
    - Tolstoy Foundation, Tolstoy, Alexandre, 1950 (Box 1)
    - U, 1947; 1950 (Box 1)
    - W, 1938; 1940-1941,; 1947-1949 (Box 1)
    - Unidentified, 1937; 1942,; 1944,; 1947,; undated (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - 1942, 1947; 1948,; 1953,; undated (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Award, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Contract, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Original sketch, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Photographs Derujinsky and son Gleb, 1931; undated (Box 1)
  - Of work and others, 1937; undated (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Church bulletins, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition notices, 1926; 1953,; 1961,; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings about, 1926; 1930,; 1937,; 1942,; 1958,; undated (Box 1)
  - Notice of election, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlet, with reproduction of work, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlet about, with reproductions of work, undated (Box 1)
  - Program, 1931 (Box 1)